<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached afore Thomas Andrews Lord Maior and the aldermen, sheriffs &amp;c. of the honorable corporation of the citie of London in which discourse is held forth I. The order, method, and succession of times and things both good and evil ... as an explanation of his former sermon before the said honorable assembly upon Octob. 8, 1650. 2. A touch upon the two witnesses. 3. An iconism or picture of the present apostacie in England. 4. A systeme of symptomes of them that will have the spiritual falling - sickness to depart from the faith / by Nathanael Homes.</title>
            <author>Homes, Nathanael, 1599-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44285</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2575</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29231</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10963761</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10963761</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46155</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44285)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46155)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1386:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached afore Thomas Andrews Lord Maior and the aldermen, sheriffs &amp;c. of the honorable corporation of the citie of London in which discourse is held forth I. The order, method, and succession of times and things both good and evil ... as an explanation of his former sermon before the said honorable assembly upon Octob. 8, 1650. 2. A touch upon the two witnesses. 3. An iconism or picture of the present apostacie in England. 4. A systeme of symptomes of them that will have the spiritual falling - sickness to depart from the faith / by Nathanael Homes.</title>
                  <author>Homes, Nathanael, 1599-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. and J.C.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Left as a testimony and protest of the author against the evils of this present age."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46155:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46155:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A SERMON Preached afore</hi> THOMAS ANDREWS <hi>LORD MAIOR, And the Aldermen, Sheriffs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of the honorable Corporation of the Citie of</hi> LONDON, <hi>At</hi> PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LS; <hi>on the Lords day,</hi> Feb. <hi>2. 1650.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Doctor NATHANAEL HOMES, Teacher to the Church at</hi> Mary Staynings, <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In which Diſcourſe is held forth,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1</hi> The Order, Method, and Succeſsion of <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Things,</hi> both <hi>good</hi> and <hi>evil,</hi> that are to come to paſs before the next appearance of Chriſt; as an explanation of his former Sermon before the ſaid honorable Aſſembly, upon <hi>Octob. 8. 1650.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2</hi> A touch upon the <hi>Two Witneſſes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3</hi> An Iconiſm or Picture of the preſent <hi>Apoſtacie</hi> in England.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4</hi> A Syſteme of Symptomes of them that will have the ſpiritual Falling-ſickneſs to depart from the Faith.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Left as a</hi> Teſtimony <hi>and</hi> Proteſt <hi>of the</hi> Author, <hi>againſt the Evils of this preſent Age.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>London, <hi>Printed by</hi> I. R. <hi>and</hi> J. C. <hi>1650.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:46155:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46155:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful <hi>Jaſper Draper, John Blackwel, Samuel Harſenet,</hi> and <hi>William Hulme,</hi> Wardens of the Right Worſhipful Company of GROCERS of <hi>London;</hi> And to the reſt of that worthy Company.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N anſwer to Deſires, I have printed this Sermon, and bequeathed it to you alſo; who (that I might acknowledge your great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to me, and your favour to the preſent Government therein) were the <hi>Primum mobile,</hi> the <hi>Firſt movers</hi> of printing my former Sermon, (to you alſo bequeathed)
<pb facs="tcp:46155:3"/>which ſo far taking your ſpirits (as you then much expreſſed) I thought it neceſſary to catch hold of this happie opportunity, to explain That by This, in ſhewing you as well the <hi>black ſide,</hi> as the <hi>bright ſide</hi> of the <hi>cloud</hi> of future times; and ſo your judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments might be ſet upright in the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion and expectation of thoſe things; to <hi>rejoyce in Chriſt,</hi> but with a holy filial <hi>trembling:</hi> Do as <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſent word to the threatning Empreſs; <hi>Ego nil niſi pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum timeo:</hi> Fear ſin, and then fear no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Your <hi>reverence</hi> of Christ ſhall be then filled with rejoycing that <hi>his</hi> day is coming, to beat down all his enemies, and advance his Saints upon earth afore the ultimate glorifying of you, and him, who ſubſcribes himſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble ſervant in Chriſt Jeſus, NATHANAEL HOMES.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Studie at</hi> Mary Staynings, <hi>London.</hi> 
                  <date>Feb. <hi>12. 1650.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46155:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Theſſ. 2.3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Let no man deceive you, by any means. For, <hi>that day ſhall not come,</hi> except there come a falling away first, and that Man of Sin be revealed, the Son of Perdition.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>chapter</hi> is happily divided from the reſt; it diſtinctly containing the ſecond part of thi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Epiſtle, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Propheſying</hi> of the Prognoſtick Antecedents, fore-running near before the next <hi>Appearance of Christ,</hi> with their appendices &amp; Appurtenances.</p>
            <p>An Error of ſome of the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> that <hi>the Day of Christ,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>was then even as preſent, Verſ.</hi> 2. was the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this Diſcourſe of the Apoſtle. Which he begins with beſeeching and obteſting them, (<hi>Verſ.</hi> 1.) by the <hi>future</hi> coming of Chriſt, that they would not be ſhaken in minde, as if he were then <hi>preſently</hi> coming, though (as in all Ages down to us) ſome would aſſert it, (<hi>Verſ.</hi> 2.) as pretending their own <hi>ſpirit</hi> of Propheſie, or ſome <hi>word, viz.</hi> Tradition; or ſuppoſitious <hi>Epistles</hi> of the Apoſtles. But, ſaith the Apoſtle, them that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade that, decline ye; for they go about to <hi>deceive</hi> you. Becauſe that Day cannot come, unleſs ſuch and ſuch things firſt come to paſs; and ſo he ſmoothly ſlides into our Text, and the Propheſie of the <hi>falling away</hi> of the ſeeming <hi>Christian,</hi> and the <hi>revealing</hi> of the <hi>Anti-christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> before the next Appearance of Chriſt. <hi>Let no man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>by any means,</hi> for that Day
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46155:4"/>ſhall not come, <hi>except there come a falling away first, and that man of ſin be revealed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee by the <hi>change</hi> of the Letter in your Bibles, how much is ſupplied by our Tranſlators, <hi>viz. Day ſhall not come</hi> is not in the <hi>Greek:</hi> but are the true ſenſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Text, and therefore ſupplied by other Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators, both of the beſt <hi>Latins</hi> and others. And they do it, becauſe, ſay ſome, here is an <hi>Apoſiopeſis,</hi> an <hi>Ellipſis,</hi> ſay others.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>The Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tator on this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle in</hi> Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies <hi>works ſaith, that ſome</hi> Syriack <hi>Copy ſo ſupplyes words,</hi> viz. Syrus (inquit) Ne quis vos decipiat ullo modo, nam niſi venerit prius defectio, &amp; reveletur ſilius hominis peccati, ſilius perditionis, ſcilicet non inſtabit Dies ille Domini. <hi>Howbeit I find them not any how ſo ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in either of my two</hi> Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack <hi>Coſies.</hi>
               </note> But what need of all this? To me the <hi>Greek</hi> it ſelf duly <hi>pointed,</hi> and rendred, is able ſufficiently to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it ſelf. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. Correct the pointing (for we had need ſometimes, as <hi>John</hi> 15.2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) and put the firſt Coma at <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and then the ſenſe runs ſmoothly and fully thus; <hi>Let no man deceive you by any means, that ſo it is,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> as <hi>Verſ.</hi> 2. that <hi>the Day of Christ is at hand</hi>) <hi>except there come a falling away first,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>There are ſome ſingular Elegancies and Emphaſes in the words, 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Two Negatives</hi> are put in the Dehortation, whoſe properties are more vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to deny, and forbid; as that we may truly render the Apoſtle, according to the Idiome of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> thus; <hi>Let no man by no means deceive you.</hi> Intimating vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that thence to ſucceeding Ages there would be much danger of many <hi>deceiving</hi> and <hi>being deceived,</hi> that <hi>Christs ſecond Coming</hi> was fulfilled afore it was. And this Deceit would peep up under many ſhapes, as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (rendred here <hi>means</hi>) may alſo ſignifie. We ſhall view this thouſand-ſhap'd <hi>Proteus</hi> better afterwards. 2. The <hi>falling away</hi> in our <hi>Engliſh,</hi> is in the <hi>Greek</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by a word which ſignifies an <hi>odious falling</hi> away, and our <hi>Engliſh</hi> of it (if rendred word for word) exactly takes after the <hi>Greek</hi> for caſting an <hi>odium</hi> upon it; For 'tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Apostaſie.</hi> The <hi>Arabick</hi> keeps the ſame. The
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:46155:4"/>
               <hi>Syriack</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies <hi>Rebellion.</hi> For <hi>Apostates</hi> uſually do not onely fall away <hi>from</hi> the Truth, but alſo <hi>against</hi> the Truth<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb. 6.6.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Fall <hi>againſt.</hi> As the <hi>Greeks</hi> ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Contrary to reaſon, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. A tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor againſt the Law. And the Apoſtle adds in that <hi>Heb. 6.6.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which is <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt</hi> the Truth with a witneſs.</note> 3. <hi>Revealed,</hi> and the <hi>Greek</hi> of it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, are near kin to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Book of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> both <hi>name</hi> and <hi>thing, viz.</hi> This <hi>man of ſin,</hi> and of <hi>perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> muſt be <hi>revealed</hi> as ripe in ſin for <hi>perdition,</hi> according to the <hi>Revelation, Chap.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp; Chap.</hi> 17. before Chriſts next coming. Which <hi>Man of ſin</hi> is expreſſed with the greateſt Emphaſis, of Emphaſis upon Emphaſis, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e. That ſame</hi> man of <hi>the ſin,</hi> that <hi>ſame ſon</hi> of the <hi>perdition.</hi> And the <hi>Greek</hi> of <hi>perdition</hi> is of the kindred of that <hi>Greek</hi> name of Anti-chriſt (<hi>Rev.</hi> 9.11.) <hi>Apollyon.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>Hebrew</hi> name there anſwers exactly.</note> This <hi>Feast</hi> (as the <hi>Revelation</hi> oft cals him) is both actively and paſſively, <hi>The Man of ſin,</hi> and <hi>Son of perdition,</hi>
               <note n="**" place="margin">
                  <hi>Illud ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, &amp; Homo perditus;</hi> as the purer <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins</hi> name, one deſperatly wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for ruine.</note> He <hi>cauſeth,</hi> and <hi>is</hi> ſin and perdition. The cauſe in <hi>others;</hi> the object in <hi>himſelf. Son</hi> in <hi>Hebrew</hi> applied to <hi>things</hi> as in the Text, ſignifies inherence and propriety of the thing to that man.</p>
            <p>I think it long this while I am in the Bark and Shell of the Text. Let us ſhew you briefly the pith and ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell. I am not willing, though it would be eaſie to ſhew you the <hi>variety</hi> of Gloſſes of the <hi>Greek ancient and pious Fathers,</hi> but rather (to my light) ſtrike point blank up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>verity</hi> of the native ſenſe.</p>
            <p>Before the next Appearance of Chriſt, two Signes ſhall precede as fore-runners, <hi>Apostaſie,</hi> and Anti-chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>Impiety,</hi> both <hi>tranſcending,</hi> and ſurpaſſing. For 'tis as well emphatically ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The</hi> or <hi>that</hi> Apoſtaſie; as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The</hi> or <hi>that</hi> Man of ſin. And both inferring one another, like Scales. If profeſſion of Chriſtianity go down, Anti-chriſtianiſme riſeth up. If Anti-chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme ſtands up, aſcends; viſible Chriſtianity fals down, and deelines. The Apoſtle ſpeaks both in a breath, not putting ſo much as a period, or half period point be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46155:5"/>And after in this Chapter proſecutes them, as reciprocally, by turns, inferring one another.<note n="*" place="margin">So in <hi>Ver. 10</hi> after the Text.</note> Men hear the Truth, but not <hi>receive the love of the Truth;</hi> they are out of love with it; <hi>Therefore the Man of ſin is let to appear: He openly acts his power, ſignes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives ſuch with his unrighteouſneſs and lyes.</hi> This the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of nature of theſe, in the Apoſtles following pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Apostaſie,</hi> and this <hi>Diſcovery revealine</hi> Anti-chriſt are both twofold (here hinted, and elſewhere more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained) twilled together, like the Legs of two Wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, claſping for a Combat. The firſt <hi>Apostaſie</hi> is not onely from the outward ſerious practiſe of Religion, but alſo from the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of Faith, and the hiſtorical, or temporary <hi>Faith</hi> of Doctrine, (as elſewhere we have more enlarged<note n="*" place="margin">Doemonolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie <hi>or</hi> Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of the crying Evils of the preſent Times.</note>) yea, and by that means gradually to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtatiſe from a <hi>fundamental</hi> Faith, that there is <hi>one true God,</hi> JEHOVAH, that hath his <hi>throne in Heaven, and the Farth for his foot-ſtool;</hi> and yet (many) have a <hi>diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical</hi> Faith, <hi>implicitly,</hi> at leaſt to go to the <hi>Devil</hi> in unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <hi>Astrologie, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ele<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes, Stoicheioſeis, Schemes, Cir<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> and <hi>Infernal ceremonies,</hi> to <hi>know,</hi> and <hi>do,</hi> things not revealed by God. This <hi>Apostaſie</hi> the Apoſtle here <hi>hints, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſ.</hi> 10, 11, 12. after our Text, as a Commentary upon it, touching the word <hi>Apostaſie,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>They received not the love of the Truth, that they might be ſaved. For this came God ſent them ſtrong Deluſions, that they ſhould beleive a <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; that they all might be damned, who beleived not the Truth, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this, this ſame Apoſtle, in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2. lays wide open, and ſtrikes home thus: <hi>Now the Spirit ſpeaketh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, that in the later <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imes ſome ſhall depart from the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ITH, giving heed to ſeducing ſpirits, and DOCITRINES of DEVILS, ſpeaking lyes in hypocriſie, having their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46155:5"/>CONSCIFNCES SEARED WITH AN HOT IRON.</hi> This added, fully reacheth this latitude of the firſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſie; which though it ſeems to wreſtle <hi>against</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-chriſtianiſme, yet doth but <hi>liſt it up.</hi> For by the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of this Apoſtaſie, Anti-chriſtianiſme takes its turn to be advanced, and therein is the firſt <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of Anti-chriſt (as the Text ſpeaks) that is, Anti-chriſt ſhall be <hi>revealed</hi> in his <hi>power</hi> and <hi>glory</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">So the <hi>Greek</hi> Fathers gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, though I liſt not to name them.</note> (as the blinde Worlds power and glory<note n="**" place="margin">Rev. 13.3. <hi>All</hi> the world wondered af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Beaſt.</note>) as our Apoſtle ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently hints in the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>erſes</hi> after the Text, as a Commentary upon it, touching that <hi>revealing; that ſame man of ſin</hi> (ſ<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith the Apoſtle, according to the <hi>Creek) and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of perdition be revealed, that ſame oppoſer and exalter of himſelf above all that is called God, or is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped; even to hi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſitting over the Temple of God as God, ſhewing himſelf that he is God; and now ye know what with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth that he might be revealed in his time.</hi> That is, the <hi>being</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of <hi>the Roman</hi> Emperour hindered Anti-chriſt then, from appearing in that dominion, power, and glory, as to be <hi>above all that is called God,</hi> &amp;c. that is, above all Magiſtracy. To which as he attains, there is added a <hi>ſecond Apostaſi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> he draweth after him the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Earth, from their due Subjection to their own chief Magiſtracy, to adore and <hi>worſhip him, Rev.</hi> 13.8. And this our Apoſtle ſufficiently hinteth<note n="*" place="margin">Though we n<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me not the whole ſtream of the <hi>Latin</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> generally running this way:</note> unto us in <hi>Verſ.</hi> 9. and 10. After in that he ſaith, This ſame <hi>Oppoſer</hi> of all other powers ſhall come <hi>after the working of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> with all <hi>power,</hi> and <hi>deceivableneſs.</hi> Should ſeem he ſhall <hi>deceive</hi> many with <hi>all</hi> his falſe Principles, and draw them after him, to ſubmit to <hi>his power;</hi> till at laſt follows a <hi>ſecond Revelation</hi> of that Man of ſin Anti-chriſt; revealing him in his intolerable <hi>impiety, tyranny,</hi> and <hi>enmity,</hi> not onely againſt the <hi>Christianity</hi> of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leivers, but againſt the <hi>natural liberty of mankinde.</hi> So
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46155:6"/>that this ſecond <hi>Revelation</hi> of him, Legs down, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrows the <hi>first Revelation</hi> of him. And repays his cauſing the former Apoſtaſies from Conſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and due ſubjection to Magiſtrates, with an <hi>Apostaſie</hi> (if I may ſo call it, it being a godly Apoſtaſie) of the <hi>enlightened</hi> World from <hi>him</hi> and his pretended <hi>power,</hi> both <hi>eccleſiastical</hi> and <hi>cevil.</hi> This ſecond Revealing of him (not to lean upon modern learned, which might numerouſly be quoted) we clearly collect out of the Apoſtles words in the 8. <hi>Verſ.</hi> after our Text, as further commenting upon the extent of the word <hi>revealing.</hi> And then (ſaith he) ſhall that wicked one be <hi>revealed.</hi> How <hi>revealed?</hi> As <hi>ſtubble</hi> in a <hi>ſlame;</hi> and nearer to the words; as <hi>riches</hi> and <hi>pomp</hi> in the riotous <hi>waſting</hi> and ſpending. And as a perſon in great <hi>honor,</hi> deveſted and degraded from that honor. For (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>him ſhall the Lord conſume with the ſpirit of his mouth, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy with the brightneſs of</hi> (to keep to the <hi>Greek) his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance.</hi> The <hi>Spirit</hi> or <hi>Breath</hi> of Chriſts mouth is his Word;<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Iſay 11.4</hi> The <hi>Chalde</hi> on that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter expounds the <hi>Spirit</hi> or <hi>Breath</hi> of his mouth, to be his <hi>Word.</hi>
               </note> and his Spirit accompanying it (as 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.) And his appearance is as well <hi>ſpiritual</hi> in the effect of his Word and Spirit upon the hearts of men drawing them from Anti-chriſt, and <hi>providential</hi> in ordering things to that end, as <hi>perſonal</hi> in his viſible coming; next before which <hi>perſonal,</hi> his <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and <hi>providential</hi> ſhall be moſt eminently conſpicuous, to a glorious <hi>brightneſs</hi> in the eyes of the generality of all men. So that before them, in their eſteem, the pomp, glory, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, power, authority, dominion, majeſty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of <hi>Anti-chriſt</hi> ſhall be blotted out as a fair writing, or melt away as a great eſtate rioted to nothing, and made <hi>void,</hi> as <hi>non ens;</hi> as the <hi>Greek</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> expendere, delere, &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquare, irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum facere, abro<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are.</note> well imports. The Goſpel ſhall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt ſuch freedom, comfort, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in oppoſition to Anti-chriſt, and providence ſhall ſo ſerve that end, that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46155:6"/>men ſhall infinitely vilifie him; untill at laſt that be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.16. <hi>The ten horns hate the Whore, make her deſolate, and naked, eat her fleſh, and burn her with fire.</hi> That is, the <hi>Nations</hi> that were formerly ſubject to him, that were formerly his <hi>horns</hi> of power to arm him with might, now ſhall turn their power againſt him to his ruine. For though they be called <hi>Kings, Verſ.</hi> 11. yet the meaning cannot be Kings properly, for that the holy Ghoſt tels us there in the 10. <hi>Verſe,</hi> thoſe Nations ſhould change their Government often; as <hi>from Kings to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, Dictator, Triumvirs, &amp;c.</hi> And experience ſuggeſts that ſeverall Nations that have departed from <hi>Anti-chriſt,</hi> have no King.<note n="*" place="margin">Switzers, Helvetians, <hi>Low Countries.</hi>
               </note> And therefore the ten ho<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> muſt ſignifie ſo many Nations, by thoſe chief Powers the People ſhall ſet up, in whom under God, all civil po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is radicated; and is planted (for uſe and ſhelter to a State) in him or them to whom the people by an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly general conſent ſhall delegate it. There is no Rule in Scripture to conſtitute any Form of civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be <hi>jure divino,</hi> and unchangeable. The Apoſtle uſeth firſt the word <hi>Apoſtaſie,</hi> becauſe its native ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation denoting the <hi>ſhrinking and ſlinking of Souldiers from their. General unto the Enemy,</hi> the tranſlating and transferring thereof to the Apoſtaſie meant (as we have heard) in this Text, is very apt, elegant, and emphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal. And ſecondly, he uſeth the word <hi>revealing,</hi> becauſe the beginning of Antichriſt was in a <hi>Myſtery, Verſ.</hi> 7. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Text, that is <hi>hiddenly.</hi> But Chriſt by his <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>providence</hi> ſhould <hi>reveal</hi> him. <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelation</hi> (as one ſaith) <hi>writ</hi> the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of Anti-chriſt, <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtles the <hi>Commentary.</hi> And both (our experience can tell us) are dayly more and more expounded, by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>providence</hi> wheeling Kingdoms and States to that effect. And thirdly, the Apoſtle cals the Race and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46155:7"/>of Anti-chriſt, the <hi>man of ſin,</hi> the <hi>ſon of perdition,</hi> as if but one man. Firſt, becauſe ſtill (as their main prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal) one man is the abſolute Head, and chief of all that Monſter and monſtrous Body, whether <hi>Turk</hi> or <hi>Pope.</hi> Though both one<note n="*" place="margin">They are one in <hi>deſent</hi> both of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Religion. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> by one of his Parents being a <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile,</hi> by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a <hi>jew:</hi> and <hi>Mahomet</hi> and a <hi>Popish</hi> Monk invented his <hi>Alcoran</hi> or Religion. And from the <hi>Pope</hi> he took his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king off three horns from the ten, <hi>Dan. 7.</hi>
               </note> Antichriſt; In <hi>deſcent,</hi> in <hi>dominion,</hi> in the <hi>Iconiſme</hi> or deſcription in the next Verſe after the Text, <hi>viz. Sitting over the Temple of God, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="**" place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Turk <hi>ſitting over the</hi> material Temple <hi>at</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem; <hi>as the</hi> Pope <hi>of</hi> Rome <hi>over</hi> Chriſtians, <hi>the</hi> ſpiritual <hi>Temple.</hi>
               </note> Though they pretend, the <hi>Turk</hi> ſomething, the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ope</hi> more, to honor Chriſt, and to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>for</hi> Chriſt, (as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſometimes ſignifies, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o.</hi> 1.16.) yet they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>againſt</hi> Chriſt, (as the word is intended and explained, 1 <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o.</hi> 2.22.) And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the Apoſtle ſpeaks of Anti-chriſt, as if but one, becauſe originally, collectively, and repreſentatively in the eſteem of God, there are but <hi>two men</hi> from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the World to the end there of. <hi>Adam</hi> is called the <hi>firſt</hi> man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.45, 47. Chriſt in the ſame place is called not only the <hi>ſecond</hi> man, but alſo the <hi>laſt</hi> man. And ſo all the ſons of men in all Generations are to be <hi>reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to,</hi> and <hi>conſidered in</hi> one of theſe two. <hi>Sinners</hi> to and in <hi>Adam</hi> (fallen) the <hi>firſt man;</hi> and <hi>Beleivers</hi> to and in <hi>Christ,</hi> the <hi>ſecond</hi> and <hi>laſt man;</hi> as it is the whole Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and the main intended Deſign in that Diſcourſe of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 12. to the end of the Chapter: and punctually and home the Apoſtle tels us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.11. that all Beleivers <hi>are to be</hi> RECKONED <hi>in Chriſt.</hi> Yea, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. he boldly eals the <hi>Church</hi> by the name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as of old did the Prophet <hi>Jeremy, Chap.</hi> 33. <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. <hi>And this is the name wherewith SHE ſhall be called, The Lord our Righteouſneſs.</hi> Which is the Name, the ſame Prophet in <hi>Chapter</hi> 23. <hi>Verſe</hi> 6. gives to <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But ſinners have a twoſold conſideration, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a double notion; one <hi>general,</hi> in their corrupt <hi>natural</hi> condition, as <hi>diſ-obedient</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> contrary to the Law, and ſo they are <hi>Adam,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.47, 48. <hi>The firſt man is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46155:7"/>of the earth, as is the earthy ſuch are they that are earthy.</hi> The other notion is more <hi>ſpecial,</hi> as ſinners are under, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in a <hi>moral</hi> ſtate and acting of <hi>nubeleif,</hi> refuſing <hi>Chriſt,</hi> contraay to the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> and ſo they are all <hi>Anti-chriſt,</hi> limbs and members of the Anti-chriſtian Head, though ſome parts are more remote and leſs quickened by that Head. Thus Saint <hi>John</hi> in his Epiſtles doth much inculcate; as in the place but now mentioned, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.22, 23. <hi>He is Antichriſt that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth the Father and the Son. Whoſoever denieth the Son, the ſame hath not the Father:</hi> therefore there are many Antichriſts now of thoſe <hi>called</hi> Chriſtians. For they <hi>ſleight</hi> Chriſt at the leaſt: and <hi>Verſ.</hi> 18. of the ſame Chapter, <hi>Antichriſt ſhall come; now are there many Antichriſts. They went out from us, becauſe they were not of us.</hi> Obſerve, the <hi>Departers</hi> from religious <hi>perſons</hi> and <hi>practiſes,</hi> from the holy <hi>Church,</hi> and the holy <hi>Rule,</hi> are called <hi>Antichriſts.</hi> So <hi>chap.</hi> 4.3. <hi>Every ſpirit that confeſſeth not that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, is not of God, and this is that ſpirit of Antichriſt; and is even now already in the World.</hi> The ſame in 2 <hi>Eph. v.</hi> 7. Now we know by 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Men may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Godlineſs, though they keep the form:</hi> by <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.20, A man may have a <hi>form of knowledge,</hi> yet be, and act as a great <hi>Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſour:</hi> by <hi>Tis.</hi> 1.16, <hi>Men may profeſs they know God, but in Works deny him.</hi> And 'tis granted by all (generally) that are not <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or <hi>Heathens,</hi> the <hi>Papacy</hi> and all its Members holding Juſtification by Works, to be Antichriſtian, though they do in words acknowledge Chriſt for a Saviour. So that (to our point in hand) all that refuſe Chriſt, believe not in him, are more or leſs <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> For in ſubſtance of Religion he that is not for Chriſt is againſt him; though in <hi>natural</hi> or <hi>civil circumſtances</hi> (as to ſerve Chriſt, though we be not in his perſonal preſence) <hi>Not to be againſt Chriſt is to be with him.</hi> It hath been ſomething irkſom to me (for your ſakes) that I have been ſo long in the Explanation of the Text, abſent from the <hi>doctrine</hi> which is my Errand, and your charge to be carried with you. But you ſee, it was a Cabinet lockt; till opened you could not have the Jewell. <hi>That,</hi> I ſhall
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46155:8"/>now give you in the <hi>main,</hi> though I (that am <hi>here</hi> leſs then the <hi>Poets</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>A man of a day;</hi> couched to an <hi>hour</hi>) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand to gather up all the <hi>ſmall Bracelets</hi> that might go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with it. I muſt omit Obſervations upon ſeveral words, and tell you my Deſigne from the heart of the Text,<note place="margin">The obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</note> this doctrinal point: What ever many deem and dream, yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>the next Appearance of Chriſt there will be a falling away of Hypocrites, obſcuring Chriſtianity, and a revealing of Antichrist: There will be an Apoſtaſie from Piety, and a revelation of the man of iniquity. Profeſſion of Religion will have the falling ſickneſs; and Antichriſtianiſme a recovery; the riſe of Hereſie and Impiety, and the ruine of Godlineſs will eminently appear, aſore Chriſt the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time appears; and this defection ſhall be attended with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</hi> Take it in which form of words you pleaſe, ſo as you carry with you the thing. 'Tis not a Point ſelected, whereon to ſhew learning or eloquence (if I had them wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the naming) or to vent my ſelf (too common a ſin with us) but (God is witneſs) laid upon my ſpirit, with deep im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, by the hand of God, out of love to my Nation, to warn them, that as the <hi>Jews</hi> after Conqueſt of Kings and Nations, they do not periſh by their own ſins. Here is (though ſelf-flatterers will dote of ſtrange things) <hi>Perdition</hi> in the Text as well as <hi>ſin:</hi> and for the <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> in the Text, <hi>periſhing</hi> and <hi>damnation</hi> after the Text, <hi>ver.</hi> 10, 11, 12. Men that are ſhort ſighted (as purblinde eyes) will ſee no Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie, anſwering to the Text, but that which was neareſt at hand after the Text had ſpoken, many hundreds of years ſince. But men dream what they deſire, and love ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations as put away fear. I do not forget what I have preached, and printed, and ſtill do hope, that a glorious time is coming, and do expect that it is not very far off: but I cannot change the Scriptures, nor invert Chriſts method. It will be <hi>dark</hi> afore the <hi>Cloud ſhine as a pillar of fire.</hi> Some ſtormes and ſtreights will be, afore <hi>Iſrael</hi> get clear of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and come to <hi>Canaan.</hi> So our condition all along the <hi>Revelations.</hi> The caſe ſtands thus; as the <hi>Promiſes</hi> and their Priviledges
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46155:8"/>of <hi>good things</hi> have their ſucceſſive and gradual fulfilling, (as we have in another place demonſtrated<note n="*" place="margin">Sermon before the <hi>Lord Maior</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Day of Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving for our Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry againſt the <hi>Scots, Octob. 8. 1150.</hi>
               </note>) ſo the divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions and <hi>Prognoſticks</hi> of <hi>future evils</hi> (that ſhall in ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Ages conflict againſt the welfare of true Saints) have alſo, in a kinde of equipage, or lackeying, of a <hi>Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trical</hi> Proportion, if not <hi>Arithmetical</hi> their ſucceſſive Incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, at leaſt by-turns, and proportionable <hi>Perdition</hi> or judgement at the heels of that, till the <hi>Promiſes</hi> ſwallow up the <hi>Prognoſticks,</hi> as <hi>Aarons Serpent</hi> did that of the <hi>Inchanters. Enoch</hi> (ſhould ſeem by Saint <hi>Jude</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Jude <hi>v.</hi> 14, 12.</note>) in the ſeventh Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from <hi>Adam</hi> propheſied, <hi>That the Lord would come with ten thouſands of his Saints,</hi> What to do? <hi>To execute judgement.</hi> What is the matter? <hi>Men ſhould be found to be ungodly, ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily committing ungodly dieds; and ungodly ſinners, ſpeaking hard ſpeeches againſt God.</hi> Which Propheſie of <hi>Enoch,</hi> though it were many years after, at the time of <hi>Noahs</hi> Flood,<note place="margin">Enoch <hi>propheſied about</hi> An. Mundi 937. <hi>The Floud was</hi> An. Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di 1657. Buchole.</note> * ere it was fulfilled, was not then <hi>totall;</hi> fulfilled, but more after the time that God confirming <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the knowledge of himſelf by a <hi>ſtery Law</hi> at Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> carrying them thence, along by <hi>Seir,</hi> and <hi>Paran, &amp;c.</hi> to the overthrow of more wicked Kings and Kingdoms, of <hi>Og the King of Baſhan,</hi> and <hi>Sihon King of the Amorites.</hi> For ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> repeats <hi>Enoch</hi> his words, <hi>Deul.</hi> 32.2. and makes it the ground-work of Propheſie, that as God had ſo done againſt the wickedneſſes that did ariſe againſt <hi>Iſrael</hi> till then; ſo the moſt impious Kings and Nations in <hi>Canaan</hi> ſhould be dealt withall. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <hi>v.</hi> 2. with <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in that <hi>Chapter:</hi> and yet in this, that Propheſſe of <hi>Enoch</hi> had not powred out all its <hi>Vial;</hi> there was yet more <hi>Apoſtaſie,</hi> and <hi>ſin,</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtianiſme,</hi> to be revealed in the World, and therefore there is behinde more wrath in that <hi>Vial,</hi> to be powred out in the laſt times to ſucceed in and after the Apoſtle <hi>Judes</hi> time, to which S. <hi>Jude</hi> applied it. Thus alſo is the race of that denunciatory Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of <hi>Iſai.</hi> 11.4. <hi>The Rod of the ſtemm of</hi> Jeſſe (Chriſt Jeſus) <hi>ſhould with righteouſneſs judge the porr,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but ſmite the earth with the rod of his mouth, and with the breath of his nostrils ſlay
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46155:9"/>the wicked:</hi> which though mightily fulfilled in his perſonal preaching, and confounding the Errors of Life and Doctrine of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and making them to fall back ward with his words, <hi>I am He;</hi> and giving power to the <hi>Apostles</hi> to do Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, to the terror of the Enemies, and death upon <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphyra;</hi> yet more wickedneſſes Apoſtaſies, and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianiſme ſucceeding the time of <hi>Christ</hi> and the <hi>Apostles,</hi> muſt have of the <hi>Vial</hi> of this prophetical threat powred out upon them, as our Apoſtle in the 8. <hi>Verſe</hi> after our Text doth punctually apply this place of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to the Apoſtaſies and Antichriſtianiſme to follow his Times, and down ward. Firſt, he puts <hi>Apostaſie,</hi> and next <hi>Antichristianiſme: Apostaſie</hi> leads the Dance, from an <hi>Almain</hi> to a <hi>Coranto,</hi> I mean from bad to worſe, and <hi>Antichrist</hi> follows, revealing himſelf in the fame of riſe, till he be revealed in the flame of his ruine.</p>
            <p>Without furher preamble, the Syſtem and frame of this <hi>Mystery of iniquity</hi> (as the Context calls it) is thus; the foundation and root of Apoſtaſie is <hi>perſonal,</hi> in the graceleſs, ſinfull hearts of Hypocrites: the ſuperſtructure and limbs are the concurrence of the generality of a Nation to ſpeak that Language, and act that converſation as ſuits to apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing, or falling away, more or leſs; till at laſt it benear oeconomical and univerſal; that Chriſtendom (as they call it) be for the moſt quite cold in their affections, and corrupt in their very Principles as well as in their Practiſes. And though at a time, like an houſe on fire, ſome peices falling, or a few Buckets powred on, do damp, and obſcure the flame for preſent, yet anon it breaks out worſe, till the whole be pulled down: and thus it gets head again, by riſing in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſhapes, and when it hath gone over all ſorts; then an old one riſeth up, as a new Faſhion: all which proceſs and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Apostaſie</hi> and <hi>Antichristianiſme,</hi> notwithſtanding ſome impedings, or diſcountenance, is ſenſibly perceived by them that are ſpiritual, <hi>Living Creatures</hi> (<hi>Revel.</hi> 4.) <hi>that have eyes as well within as without.</hi> Theſe can ſee, that though all Roots of goodneſs be not kill'd, yet the Bloſſomes and young fruit of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46155:9"/>of the Trees are generally blaſted. Though <hi>Autume</hi> Plants and Herbs be not as in <hi>Winter,</hi> altogether leaf-leſs, without all appearance, yet lifeleſs, without ſpirit and vigor.</p>
            <p>You will ſay, How ſhall theſe things be, now forward,<note place="margin">The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> which have not been ſo, palpably, theſe two or three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years backward or more? If this be true, thank Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, Oppreſſions, Afflictions for it. But beſides the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Cauſe of <hi>Apostates</hi> and <hi>Antichrists;</hi> 'tis the nature of the <hi>Beast,</hi> and property of the <hi>Diſeaſe,</hi> viz. <hi>Wicked men and Seducers grow worſe and worſe, deceiving and being deceived, till their folly and madneſs be made manifest to all men,</hi> (2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.9, 10, 11, 12, 13.) I ſay, beſides this common Cauſe, that ſuch, in longer time, grow riper in their ſins, there are ſpecial Reaſons now nearer the end, afore <hi>Christs Appearance,</hi> to wit, now God changeth his hand, ever and anon, to truſt Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that have pofeſſed the Goſpel, with <hi>Liberty</hi> (Civil and Spiritual) a thing which for many Ages they have not known, and therefore are utterly unskilled to rightly uſe it. And from hence as men half-famiſhed coming to full Diet, they ſurfet and break out into ſpiritual Scabs, and Botches. Their Liberty to the generality of them proves but as a Lightening afore Death; their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying but as the bright Glance and Glare of a Spark or Snuff before it goes out. The Liberty they triumphed in, as if they would improve it to great advantages in matters of Religion, proves but an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity (none then controlling their Opinions and way of Profeſſion) for them to become <hi>any thing,</hi> till at laſt they become <hi>nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further, the rotten-hearted (the moſt of men) bad enough of themſelves, infecting (as I may ſay) the common air where they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, and now putrifie, cauſing ſome Saints (none being yet perfect) to be touched with a tincture of the common Contagion, ſome ſpecks of Itch, and petty ſpots appearing, as Symptomes of their ſtain alſo (ſo far) with the general Infection, thoſe rotten-hearted men take incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement thence to loath all the ſincere, and their wayes; but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce to themſelves their own licentious Liberty, &amp; baſe backſliding, a pious priviledge, a ſpirituality, a perfection. Thus as <hi>Luthers</hi> Sw<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne (of which he ſpeaks to this our purpoſe) Theſe impious Revolters joyfully grunt, gladly to nuzzle in Excrements, but contemptibly trample Gold and Jewels, and pleaſingly wallow in the Mire, becauſe ſome godly men
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:46155:10"/>by force of temptation a little trod in the dirt, but got out again. Theſe Comparers of themſelves with the worſer things of the beſt men to be worſt themſelves, never take notice of the common hour of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, brought on by themſelves; nor take any true account of the juſt circumſtances of beleivers failings, that if <hi>Solomon</hi> be carried forth to make experiment of the <hi>vanity of wine,</hi> yet ſtill he <hi>acquainted his heart with wiſdom.</hi> Nor do they look after the Saints, many, yea, thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of repentings for one ſin. <hi>David</hi> for his, pens many penitential Pſalms: how often by him recited who can tell? We are not deſtitute of Precedents to confirm this, even down to theſe times; wherein the common crowd of <hi>Profeſſors of Religion</hi> fall away to be <hi>deteſtors of Religion.</hi> And becauſe they ſee ſome weakneſſes in ſome ſingle Saints that adhere to Ordinances; and that no way either of <hi>Baptiſers, Presbyters,</hi> or <hi>Congregations,</hi> is perfect, therefore they adore their own <hi>New-nothing,</hi> or their <hi>worſe then nothing</hi> in Religion, to be a great religious ſomething. For to a many, a freedome of their ſpirits to ſin, is by them cried up for a ſanctity. So long ſince as <hi>Constantine the great</hi> we have a draught, and platforme of the manner, means, and meaſure of Apoſtaſie and Antichriſtianiſme, before aſſerted. He put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a period to the <hi>ten Perſecutions,</hi> about the year after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 313. thence forward for his time, giving liberty, peace, promotions, and donations to the Churches, how odiouſly anon after, brake out and ſprang up <hi>Papal pride, Arrian Antichriſtianiſme,</hi> and the thouſand headed <hi>Hydra</hi> of Hereſie; too much to be counted, name and thing, in one hour, as pious and learned <hi>Epiphanius</hi> about 50 years after, and S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> about 30 years after him have declared. When a dark cloud of <hi>War</hi> began again to overſhadow the Earth; fulneſs of troubles in many places; God raiſing <hi>Carolus Magnus</hi> (accounted to have been a wonderfull religions Prince<note n="*" place="margin">Carolus Magnus fuit ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum religioſus princeps. Epit. Hiſt. Fccleſ. Magde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg. Ad annum 383. c<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. 3.</note>) about the year 760 after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as a mighty Warrier, and ſuccesfull Deſtroyer of the open Enemies of Religion, and withall exceeding indulgent and beneficial to the <hi>Churches</hi> (which then were many in many Countries<note n="**" place="margin">Ibid. pag. 1. Epit. Hiſtor. Hiſt. Eccl. Magd. ad ann. 788, 789, 791, &amp;c.</note>) how abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minably after a while did thouſands <hi>apoſtatiſe, Pontifical pride</hi> begins more to ſwell, and <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and <hi>Superſtation</hi> more to fret and ſpread like a Gangrene and Leproſie. <hi>Multi jam errorres, &amp;c. many Errors had now crept into the Church of Chriſt. The</hi> Hunnes <hi>revolted from Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion to Ethniciſme. Tum religio chriſtiana, &amp;c. Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then was much contaminated with many Superſtitions;</hi> with infinite more in the next <hi>Century,</hi> and downwards. Theſe doubtleſs might be part of the Apoſtles meaning in our Text, and in his Explanation,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:46155:10"/>1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> numbering the kindes of Apoſtaſies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be in the <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Times,</hi> (mark the Phraſe according to the <hi>Greek</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. But theſe are not all our Apoſtles ſenſe and intent. Theſe afore named in the ſaid Times are but beginnings, and Landskips, and petty Maps to that Ocean, and world of wickedneſs that was to follow in future. For ſurely, when our Apoſtle, &amp; the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> do afterwards, by the ſame Spirit, ſpeak in a higher Key, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſaying, <hi>In the laſt Dayes.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3. in a yet higher Key, ſaying, <hi>In the laſt of Dayes:</hi>
               <note n="**" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and do immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſubjoyn theſe Propheſies of <hi>worſer</hi> Impieties near to the <hi>Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Chriſt,</hi> (2 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. &amp; 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. compared with 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10.) they muſt needs intend to ſignifie to us a further <hi>Apoſtaſie of Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors,</hi> and <hi>Revelation of Antichriſt; viz.</hi> An (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as 'tis in the Text) eminent, a <hi>the</hi> or <hi>that</hi> ſame <hi>Apoſtaſie,</hi> and <hi>Revelation</hi> of Antichriſt, of the ſin of the perdition, ſome <hi>general</hi> and <hi>grand</hi> defection. And ſo doth S. <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelation</hi> carry on the ſucceſſion &amp; ſuccretion, the length and latitude of that defection: for in the 13. Chapter. The <hi>Beaſt</hi> hath <hi>power</hi> to act two and forty moneths, <hi>i.e.</hi> 12. hundred &amp; 60. Dayes, <hi>i. e.</hi> Years, <hi>blaspheming God, and adored of men,</hi> more or leſs. This <hi>John</hi> propheſied about an hundred years after <hi>Christ:</hi> ſo that this (if we could ſay no more) carries the Pedigrecc to 1360. years after <hi>Christ.</hi> But we can out of Scripture ſay more to this. Antichriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme in <hi>Pauls</hi> time was but in a <hi>Mystery.</hi> The <hi>Hinderer</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: alii, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> (the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Emperour ſitting in the Throne) lying in the way, and keeping under the <hi>Revelation of Antichist</hi> (as 'tis in the Context); Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt had not yet his<note n="**" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>power</hi> given to him to make war thoſe 42. moneths (mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.5.) You heard before, that till 313, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Christ,</hi> the Church was under a ſore Perſecution by the Heathen <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours. But after that time Antichriſt began to appear in <hi>Arrianiſme,</hi> and Perſecution of them that were contrary minded. Then began his <hi>power,</hi> about 390. years after <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And in 410. the <hi>Hinderer,</hi> the <hi>Roman Emperour</hi> was taken away, <hi>Rome</hi> being taken and ſpoiled by the <hi>Gothes, &amp;c.</hi> All which accounts (putting 410. to 1260.) are not yet run out. So that Apoſtaſie and Revelation of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt to all effects, fruit and branches are yet in the increment and increaſe, as our wofull experience at this day can fully atteſt. And this Saint <hi>John</hi> doth further mainifeſt unto us, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the time of the fifth <hi>Vial</hi> (which is the utmoſt to which we are come, if we be come) Antichriſt hath his <hi>Throne</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">So the Greak.</note> (though then to be darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) and men are very <hi>blasphemous and impenitent,</hi> notwithſtanding the powring forth of that <hi>Vial</hi> (O that our Eares could not witneſs
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46155:11"/>ſuch Blaſphemies). And beyond this under the ſixth <hi>Vial</hi> are <hi>three un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean ſpirits like Frogs, coming out of the mouth of the Dragon, the Beast, and the falſe Prophet which are ſpirits of Devils working of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, and drawing the Kings of the Earth to Battle</hi> againſt the Saints. And laſtly, <hi>Satan ſtill reigneth, and the great City is undivided, and the Cities of the Nations ſtand, ana</hi> Babylon <hi>comes not into rememberance before the Lord, to give her the cup of the wine of the fierce wrath of God,</hi> till the ſeventh <hi>Vial</hi> be powred out, <hi>Revel.</hi> 16.17. When this is powred out, then thoſe things are done, <hi>(ibidem)</hi> and Satan is bound, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. Be ſure <hi>Amorite</hi>-Apoſtates and Antichriſts ſins muſt be firſt <hi>ripe and full,</hi> afore they receive for their ſins their total fall and ruine, which being not yet executed, no doubt but the truth of our Text by coſts and turns ſhall have its progreſs and augmentation, of further Apoſtaſie and Antichriſtianity; though here and there, now and then, by parcell they receive ſhrewd blows afore the fatal one comes. For if ye mark the Myſtery of Gods diſpenſations, and his Methode between his <hi>promiſes</hi> of good, and <hi>Prognoſtications</hi> of evil; the prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtick is progreſſive to ſuch a period; the promiſe likewiſe being ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive, overtakes it, and knocks it down; it riſeth up again, and gets more head; the promiſe again makes after it, reacheth it, and gives it another blow and wound. And thus they keep turns, till Good hath the full Victory of Evil unto its full perdition at Chriſts appearance, as you have heard and ſeen all along this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>So here is our <hi>fear</hi> and our <hi>care</hi> now brought home &amp; laid before us;<note place="margin">The Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> namely, to inquire how forward we are gone in <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> and <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity;</hi> and how far behinde Perdition is; for according to the ſtature of the defection, there attends proportionable perdition, you ſee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is written upon <hi>ſin</hi> (in the Text). <hi>Cains</hi> mark. And to <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> is added after the Text, Seduction and Damnation. And ſo as God ſaid to <hi>Cain, Evil lies at the door,</hi> the Apoſtle cries in my Text, <hi>Let no man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you.</hi> Should ſeem men are apt to be deceived about theſe things which we now diſcourſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.12, 13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.24. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.15.</note> Apt to be hardned by the <hi>deceitfulneſs of ſin,</hi> their <hi>deceitfull hearts,</hi> the <hi>depths of Satan,</hi> and the <hi>transformation of men the instruments of Satan</hi> (the Prince of Darkneſs) <hi>into Angels of light.</hi> To be ſinfully miſerable, and not to know it, is double miſery. Darkneſs and Chains.<note place="margin">The <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> In opinions and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</note> 'Tis not out of our ſight and hearing in part, that the common Crowd of Profeſſors in this preſent Age count their <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> (kicking behinde them <hi>Ordinances</hi> with the ſcorne of <hi>formes; holy converſation</hi> with the brand of <hi>Bonds</hi> and privation of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive liberty; and <hi>Christ</hi> with the reproach of a fleſhly thing) to be their ſublimity, and high perfection.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:46155:11"/>
            <p> And for <hi>Antichriſtianiſm,</hi> many they are on the other ſide who deny Chriſt to have come, been born, and ſuffered in the fleſh; (which S. <hi>John</hi> defines to be Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianiſm:) <hi>Familiſtically</hi> making him a <hi>Non-ens.</hi> And as S. <hi>John</hi> (you heard before) tells us, <hi>In denying the Son, they deny the Father alſo.</hi> And truely for <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> ſtore of them are profeſſed ones; and make the Creatures that ſhould convince them, to be God; and the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures that ſhould be their cure, to be their ſcorn. I will not name all that I know of theſe mens <hi>nefanda,</hi> words and things, leſt I ſhould tranſgreſs againſt the Word, that forbids <hi>Baalim,</hi> and <hi>Fornication, Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and other ſins, ſo much as to be <hi>named</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Hoſ. 2. v. 17. and Eph. 5.3.</note>. Theſe roots (it ſeems by Books) came out of <hi>Germany;</hi> which planted here, do like their ſoyl, and grow mightily. And beſide, the devil is as well here, as any where elſe; and can as eaſily make <hi>Judaſſes</hi> among us, as in other Nations; how much more <hi>Ananiaſſes, Maguſſes, Hyme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuſſes, Epheſians, Sardiſians?</hi> Multitudes among us heretofore ſeemingly ſound and hot in Religion, have <hi>lyed</hi> to their profeſſion, made <hi>Gain</hi> their godlineſs, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced Religion out of <hi>deſigne,</hi> made <hi>ſhipwrack of the Faith,</hi> forſaken their <hi>firſt love,</hi> entertained <hi>unſound Teachers,</hi> have onely a <hi>name</hi> of Chriſtians; and are as <hi>dead</hi> and cold in Religion, as a ſtone. Thus they are, and refuſe (a many of them) to <hi>read,</hi> or <hi>hear,</hi> or <hi>converſe</hi> with ſound profeſſors, that they may be ſure never to be better.</p>
            <p>Is this all? No.<note place="margin">In Practice.</note> Theſe are but the <hi>foundation and root;</hi> the ſuperſtructure and fruit is evils of Practice; as, Drinking, Riotouſneſs, Whoredoms, Wantonneſſes,<note place="margin">Againſt <hi>Self.</hi>
               </note> Curſings, Blaſphemies (even in Pulpit, and elſewhere) with ſuch words of alluſion to the ſacred things of Chriſt, as a pious heart hates to think. With ſome of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:46155:12"/>theſe ſins they <hi>pleaſe the fleſh;</hi> with others they <hi>ſear their conſciences,</hi> that they may never repent. And they do profeſs an inſenſibleneſs of any ſin, and to act thoſe things by principle.</p>
            <p>Are theſe all?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Againſt</hi> God.</note> No. There is another predicament or Table of high tranſgreſſions <hi>againſt God.</hi> I will name but two.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Unlawful, ſuperſtitious, and diabolical Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie.</hi> Of which becauſe I have ſpoken in Print, I ſay no more here.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Prophanation of the Lords day.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> Of which ſin, the <hi>Edict</hi> or <hi>Book of Sports</hi> was I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a main <hi>meritorious</hi> cauſe to bring our two laſt Kings to untimely ends; and the practiſe of it brought Gods judgements upon hundreds: as the Book of <hi>Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on ſinners,</hi> and that other of <hi>Gods judgements on Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath-breakers,</hi> do declare. And we are extremely guilty ſtill; Thouſands chuſing to walk in fields on the Lords day, rather then to hear the Preaching of the Word. For now they are free from enforcement to hear the <hi>Service-book,</hi> they return this for their thanks, They will hear nothing at all. And thus they daily do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>London,</hi> though the worthy Lord Maior preſent, and others formerly, have much endeavoured to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it. But let me ſay to thoſe <hi>Profaners, Tolle Diem, &amp; tolle Deum cultus.</hi> Take away the <hi>Day,</hi> and you take away the <hi>Deity</hi> of Worſhip.</p>
            <p>Are theſe all?<note place="margin">Againſt our <hi>Neighbour.</hi>
               </note> No. There is another Predicament or Table of ſins againſt our <hi>Neighbour;</hi> Viz. <hi>Falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations, Injuſtice, Bribery, Oppreſsion, Circumvention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Have we yet All?<note place="margin">Againſt the <hi>Church</hi> of Chriſt.</note> No. There is another of ſins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Univerſal Church of Chriſt. Reproaching of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances: Diſgracing all ways of Worſhip: Questioning all Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteries, reproaching their Perſons and Offices, pining them from maintenance, and profeſsing their hope</hi> (as ſome have expreſſed) <hi>that within few years the name of Miniſter
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:46155:12"/>ſhall be odious.</hi> For teſtimony, we have their Books, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon expreſſions, and deeds. Would God <hi>all the Lords people were Prophets;</hi> or that you need not to be taught by men, but were <hi>fully taught of God.</hi> But mean while, Lord turn thoſe mens hearts; or elſe diſpoſe of us, that we may not ſee your ruine.</p>
            <p>Have we yet all?<note place="margin">Sins againſt the <hi>State.</hi>
               </note> No. There is one Predicament more of ſins againſt the <hi>State.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Self-power;</hi> every man would rule, or bring the Majeſtie of Magiſtracie as lowe as themſelves; (a dangerous preface to cutting of throats:) an <hi>Adamitiſh</hi> diabolical Levelliſm.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ends.</hi> Moſt men care for their Cabins, whiles the Ship, the Common welfare, is in danger. They are like the <hi>Romane Conſul,</hi> that was deaf with delight in his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, whiles the Drums of the enemy beat at the walls of the City.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Sycophancie,</hi> with pretence of the Common weal, to fill ones own pockets. O this State-eating, this Commonwealth-devouring!</item>
               </list> I wiſh I might ſee men go quite beyond <hi>Iehu,</hi> and, like <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> do that which all may have a ſhare in. O <hi>England,</hi> I am afraid concerning thee; and <hi>London,</hi> concerning thee. The <hi>Swedes,</hi> and that party, are fallen from their firſt zeal, and have unworthily made agreement with Antichriſtian <hi>Amalek,</hi> with whom, in ſuch a Caſe and Cauſe, no Peace was to be made. The <hi>Netherlands</hi> unhappie in their League with one limb of Antichriſt, and in their aſſiſtance of another limb of him to be their neer ill neighbour. The <hi>Scots</hi> have fallen from their own Articles, profeſſion of Reformation, and their <hi>quondam</hi> Principles, to bring Malignants to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dign puniſhment. But <hi>England</hi> and <hi>London</hi> are mightily fallen from <hi>Religion.</hi> Not long ſince you were neer the higheſt in profeſſion of Religion above all the Nations of the earth. <hi>England</hi> was the <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:46155:13"/>
               <hi>London</hi> the <hi>midſt,</hi> where were the choice trees of <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and of life.</hi> But now in many main things of Religion, ye are fallen lower then <hi>Lutherans, Papists, Iews, Turks,</hi> and <hi>Heathens;</hi> in deſpiſing Chriſt, denying the Scriptures, and profeſſed Atheiſm. <hi>England</hi> is a waſte wilderneſs of decayed Religion, and <hi>London</hi> the neſt of all unclean birds. Therefore am I afraid of the <hi>Citie of my habitation,</hi> and of the <hi>Land of my nativity.</hi> I fear not the <hi>French, Danes, Scots,</hi> &amp;c. I fear the <hi>ſins of England</hi> and <hi>London.</hi> For when <hi>Balak</hi> could not beat us, nor <hi>Balaam</hi> enchant and curſe us; we received and acted the Doctrine and Counſel of <hi>Balaam;</hi> the Nation is full of Adulteries, Corporal and Spiritual, beſide thoſe clouds of ſins afore appearing. Can God in juſtice put up theſe things at our hands, and not do by us as by <hi>Iſrael</hi> for that <hi>Balaamitiſh</hi> defection, till <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cozbi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 24.</note> and thouſands more, were deſtroyed unto death; ſome killed with a <hi>javelin,</hi> others <hi>hanged,</hi> and Four and twenty thouſand deſtroyed by the <hi>Peſtilence?</hi> What though glorious times for the Univerſal Church are not far off? <hi>England</hi> is but a ſmall <hi>ſpot</hi> of ground, and may have <hi>an hour fo temptation,</hi> and yet that deſigne little or nothing interrupted. A ſtorm of Lightning, Thunder, and Hail, may fall in the dawning of a moſt glorious fair Summers day, as it proves afterward. <hi>Iſrael</hi> was got quite out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> yet often ſinning in the way towards <hi>Canaan,</hi> were often ſorely puniſhed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. And if any Believers among them concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the ſin, they eſcaped not the puniſhment. The Lord <hi>forgave their iniquities,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 99.8.</note> 
               <hi>but took vengeance of their inventions.</hi> Yea, when <hi>Iſrael</hi> had begun to enter <hi>Canaan,</hi> and had conquered <hi>Iericho,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of the <hi>Two Witneſſes,</hi> and their time and place of lying dead and riſing.</note> yet, for a great ſin, before <hi>Ai</hi> they fall. Though the <hi>Two Witneſſes</hi> have been long time ſlaying, the Queſtion ſtill is, Whether they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:46155:13"/>have <hi>layn their three days and an half dead.</hi> Which being not yet fulfilled, it will be a Common calamity when and where it falls. And not altogether unſutable, 'tis the judgement of ſome piouſly learned, <q>
                  <hi>That the time of all the great troubles to be on the Chriſtian Gentiles is not yet over: but that there is a time yet to come, in which the Popal power ſhall dowineer over all Europe, afore its full ruine.</hi>
               </q> Their Arguments are two. The one from <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Argum.</note> in which (ſay they) is intimated a two-fold ſubjection of the ten Horns, that is, of the ten Kingdoms of <hi>Europe,</hi> to the Beaſt. The firſt in verſ. 12, 13. where it is ſaid emphatically, <hi>They,</hi> all ten of them, <hi>had one minde, ſentence, judgement, or reſolution to give their power to the beaſt.</hi> They then being all of one Religion, under the ſame groſs Ignorance and Superſtition, they were by that means all of one minde. Secondly, in verſ. 17, God <hi>put</hi> (Greek, <hi>gave</hi>) <hi>into their hearts to make</hi> (ſo again in the Greek) <hi>one minde, ſentence, judgement, or reſolution, to give their kingdom to the Beaſt.</hi> (For I am bold to obſerve this for them, That though in both places 'tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one <hi>minde, ſentence, judgement,</hi> or <hi>reſolution;</hi> yet there is this ſingular difference, that in verſ. 13. 'tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, They <hi>have</hi> one minde, ſentence, judgement, or reſolution; in verſ. 17. 'tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, To <hi>make</hi> one minde, ſentence, judgement, or reſolution. Before, from innate <hi>Principles</hi> of the ſame ſuperſtitious Religion, they <hi>were of one minde:</hi> But now, upon <hi>debate, policie, confederacie, and deſigne,</hi> they <hi>make one minde,</hi> ſentence, judgement, or reſolution.) How? Why, ſay they, the Text tells us, God <hi>gave it into their hearts to make that one minde:</hi> That is, (as 'tis ſaid in a like phraſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>God gave them up;</hi> and <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. <hi>God hardens ſome mens hearts</hi>) God <hi>gave them up in juſt judgement,</hi> that as many of the ten
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:46155:14"/>Horns as ſhould after deſtroy the <hi>Whore</hi> (ver. 16.) ſhould notwithſtanding afore that, having been enlightned, and in good meaſure delivered from Popery, revolt from that illumination and deliverance, and cloſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate, and covenant into one determination with the other of the ten Horns or Kingdoms of <hi>Europe,</hi> that continually abode in Popery. For, ſay they, Now, in verſ. 17. all the ten Horns <hi>were</hi> not of <hi>one minde,</hi> till by conſultation and agreement they <hi>made</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of one minde. Some of them (as we ſaid but now) had been enlightned, and eſcaped from Popery; but now revolt into one minde with Popiſh Kingdoms and Nations, and their powers. And this muſt be, ſay they; elſe how ſhall the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> of all Gods people lie dead <hi>three days and an half?</hi> For theſe Witneſſes of all Believers, are not found in Kingdoms that ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tined in Popery: Therefore they muſt be in Nations that once, being enlightned, departed from <hi>Rome;</hi> but (as 'twas ſaid afore) revolt again unto ſubjection to <hi>Rome.</hi> And this laſt ſubjection to <hi>Rome,</hi> is that which precedes next before the ruine of <hi>Rome,</hi> by the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>Witneſſes;</hi> who muſt riſe up, out of thoſe Nations before enlightned, though ſince revolted; but now again returning to the Truth; God ſtirring up his people to that animoſity. For not <hi>all</hi> the ten Horns or Kingdoms ſhall <hi>hate and deſtroy</hi> the <hi>Whore;</hi> becauſe 'tis expreſs, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. that <hi>ſome of them ſhall lament her ruine,</hi> But, the meaning is, that <hi>ſome</hi> of the ten Horns ſhall deſtroy her, <hi>(Synechdoche generis pro ſpecie, totius pro parte.)</hi> As 'tis ſaid with the ſame <hi>figurative</hi> ſpeech, The <hi>Thieves</hi> (that is, <hi>de ſpecie latronum,</hi> ſome of the kinde of <hi>Thieves,</hi> as well as of <hi>Souldiers,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>reviled</hi> Chriſt, though but one of them did it.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Argum.</hi>
               </note> Their other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is from <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.7. That before the total fall of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:46155:14"/>
               <hi>Babylon,</hi> even a little afore that ruine, ſhe ſhall glorifie her ſelf, ſaying in her heart, I SIT A QUEEN, AM NO WIDOW, AND SHALL SEE NO SORROW. But, ſay our Authors, 'tis not yet ſo with the Popedom. For my part, I had not time (in my ſudden warning to this work) to debate theſe things to my full ſatisfaction; nor have I time in this hour to determine how far I cloſe with theſe things in all particulars, further then to tell you, that ſo far I conceive them to be right, as in the main they make out my Text and Doctrine, That an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent falling down of Religion, and ariſing up of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtianiſm, will be before the next appearance of Chriſt; and ſutable perdition ſucceſſively will attend upon it. And both will be the more <hi>general,</hi> and <hi>high,</hi> where they are not timouſly prevented. You will ask, How ſhould there be any prevention in any degree? We anſwer out of the Text, three things. 1.<note place="margin">Three Preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware aforehand; take warning: Fear and repent. <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is the man that feareth always,</hi> (as is the general ſcope of the Text.) And our Saviour to the lapſed Churches in the ſecond and third Chapters of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> gives this antidote in the word <hi>Repent:</hi> threatens to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the Candleſtick:</hi> or to do ſo and ſo unto them, <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they did repent:</hi> and aggravates their ſin, that he gave them <hi>time to repent,</hi> and they did not: and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them to <hi>repent,</hi> and <hi>do their firſt works.</hi> It ſhould ſeem Chriſt diſtinctly requires <hi>affectionate</hi> and <hi>effectual</hi> Repentance, to prevent thoſe judgements. <hi>Affectionate,</hi> in deep workings of the affections (as the word inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates;) and <hi>effectual,</hi> in <hi>doing our former works,</hi> as tis there expreſs: Repentance, it ſhould ſeem, will avert ſuch threats. Non-repentance lets in ruine as a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge. In <hi>Revel.</hi> 16. at pouring out of one Vial,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:46155:15"/>'tis added afore the next be poured our, that <hi>they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented not</hi> at the pouring out of the former. Repentance is fully deſcribed,<note place="margin">A Motlon for days of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation.</note> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11. And to help on this, I would Parliament, and Citie, and Kingdom would not loſe their acquaintance with days of publike <hi>Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> (Now for <hi>Sins,</hi> as formerly for <hi>Judgements.</hi> The former is a weightier cauſe, and includes the buſineſs of the <hi>later:</hi>) And to go to the work afore we are whipt to it. Forcement to that duty, will neither ſpeak for our <hi>ſincerity,</hi> nor for our hopes, in the day of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn cries. Poor <hi>Nineve</hi> of Heathens ſcaped by this courſe of Repentance. Think of it, you Engliſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, and promote it. Mean while, let us be marked with the letter <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="*" place="margin">The firſt letter of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>Law, Doctrin, Inſtruction,</hi> &amp; <hi>Word,</hi> of God. Thereby ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men whoſe hearts are deeply affected with the Word of God, to judge and do according to it.</note>, T (as 'tis in the Hebrew) noting us for them that <hi>mourn, and ſigh, and cry for the abominations of the land,</hi> Ezek. 9.4.</p>
            <p>And you <hi>Senators</hi> and <hi>Judges</hi> of Seſſions and Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catures, <hi>Let juſtice be done according to the Law</hi> (as the <hi>Perſian</hi> Emperour ſaid of judging a mighty <hi>Queen,</hi> in <hi>Eſth.</hi> 1.15.) chiefly on <hi>Blaſphemers</hi> and <hi>Atheiſts;</hi> who are worſe then many <hi>Thieves</hi> you hang. And let all of us call upon our apoſtatized friends, and reclaim, or conſtrain, or reſtrain them.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2 Prevention.</note> The Text doth intimate, that all ſhall not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, to fall totally away; elſe the Apoſtles admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> had been totally vain. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us ſearch into our hearts and try our ways by the <hi>candle of the Lord,</hi> (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, meaning Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine light) whether we be of them that are like to have this Falling-ſickneſs of Apoſtacie from Religion,<note place="margin">Symptomes of the ſpiritual Falling-ſickneſs, or Apoſtacie from Religion.</note> like to fall away from our Profeſſion. I ſhall here for brevity ſake give you but Five Symptomes.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Symptome <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> is, <hi>Not to receive the LOVE of the Truth.</hi> So verſ. 10. after my Text: where 'tis not ſaid
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:46155:15"/>onely, <hi>receive THE TRUTH;</hi> but the <hi>LOVE</hi> of the Truth. <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>love</hi> of Truth, and to <hi>love</hi> it as <hi>Truth.</hi> And that, not meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be <hi>prudent, wiſe,</hi> underſtanding men; but (as 'tis there alſo) <hi>to be ſaved.</hi> And ſalvation (as S. <hi>Austin</hi> well, upon <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21.) is to be ſaved <hi>from</hi> our ſins. Truth muſt be a Science cloſed with the Stock of the heart by <hi>Love:</hi> It muſt be a Plant ſet in a <hi>moist heart,</hi> Jam. 1.21. An implanted or <hi>engrafied Word.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Thy heart and the Word muſt live, and grow up together, as a Stock and a Science or Scion: And (which is wonderful) the Science muſt change the nature of the Stock.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He whoſe heart is willing to ſin,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> Sympto<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but <hi>only</hi> 'tis reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſomething without the heart; as in <hi>Laban, Balaam,</hi> and at a time in <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Pilate;</hi> he, that very man, is like to fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; whiles his forbearance of ſin is not from inward divine principles, and diſputed in Prayer, and back'd by Faith in the death and reſurrection of Chriſt: which was the Art of <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 7. and <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. If men do not mainly by ſuch inward principles, ſo mann'd and managed, depart from ſin; but do it, ſo far as they do it, by policie, looking at outward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, they have the tokens of this Faling-ſickneſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When a man acts good with <hi>ſelf-ends,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3</hi> Symptom</note> and beyond that he doth not act, as <hi>Jehn, Judas,</hi> and <hi>Magus;</hi> he hath the ſignes he will fall away as the did. <hi>Jehn</hi> onely acted to <hi>remove that which ſtood in his way,</hi> viz. That which did impede his acceſs to the Crown, and his peaceable enjoyment of it; but not the Idol and evils of his predeceſſor. <hi>Magus</hi> profeſſed his belief, and was baptized, that he <hi>might obtain the admired gifts. Indas</hi> the longeſt laſting falſe ground, laſted as long as his <hi>gain laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> no longer. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.14, When <hi>ye howled</hi> (as alluding to <hi>dogs</hi> crying for love of their meat, not of their maſter) <hi>for corn and wine, and oil, did ye faſt unto me, even to me?</hi> And <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10.1. <hi>Iſrael is an empty vine, bringing forth fruit unto himſelf.</hi> He onely clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed himſelf gay with green leaves, unleſs he brought a few berries to ſeminate its kinde: not to ſerve the end of the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, that planted it.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:46155:16"/> 4.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ymptom.</note> Be the fruit never ſo fair, or full, if it be not from a right cauſe, root and ſtock, he will fall off as a dead branch. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.2. Point it right, thus: <hi>Every branch,</hi> (put the comma there) <hi>in me that beareth not fruit, he taketh away;</hi> and (as 'tis in <hi>verſ.</hi> 6.) <hi>is caſt forth AS A BRANCH.</hi> That is, a man will fall off, and become a <hi>tarquam-Branch,</hi> a thing that is but an <hi>AS IT WERE</hi> in Religion unleſs he be fruitful, and brings forth that fruit from a <hi>Phyſical union</hi> (as 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4, intimates) from a <hi>partaking of the divine nature,</hi> from a communication (as <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20.) of the life of Chriſt; from a ſerious frequent application of Chriſt to that very end.</p>
            <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ymptom.</note> The laſt Symptome of the ſpiritual falling-ſickneſs is, the want of that <hi>Antidote</hi> of Antidotes; <hi>oil in the veſſel,</hi> (as Chriſt calls it) <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.4. For as 'tis there in the parable, the <hi>fooliſh</hi> virgins went very far; were in the <hi>Heaven</hi> of ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>companiors to the wiſe,</hi> had <hi>lamps</hi> of much brain knowledg of divine things, with a fair <hi>moral converſation;</hi> had an <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation</hi> of Chriſt coming, (therefore took lamps and waited) had ſome <hi>awakenings of conſcience</hi> at the noiſe of Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; yet for all this becauſe they had no <hi>oil in the veſſel,</hi> that is, no infuſed habit of divine grace in the heart; no inward change, no complexion of holineſs; they fail and fall at laſt.</p>
            <p>Therefore (Chriſtians) if theſe five tokens of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual falling ſickneſs be upon us, our work of ſalvation lies yet undone;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> matter and <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ner of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tion and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>on.</note> 'tis yet to be done. A new foundation is to be layd, in floods of godly ſorrow for ſin, and in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, for paſt <hi>hypocriſie.</hi> New applications of Chriſt by faith in Goſpel promiſes offering him, are to be made; with ſtrong cries of prayer that God would give our hearts and ſouls to Chriſt, that we may be <hi>joyned to the Lord</hi> (1 Cor. 7) as <hi>one ſpirit;</hi> and ſo really cloſe with him, with mutual taking him to us and we giving up our ſelves to him, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.16. <hi>My beloved is mine, and I am his;</hi> adding to all an earneſt begging of God (as was the manner of ſincere ones, <hi>Iob, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:46155:16"/>and <hi>Pauls advice</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.) to ſearch and try us that we be not deceived. And ſtill to ſtick to this work in attendance on ordinances and duties, with Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ejaculations, and ſpiritual conteſtations between God and us, and us and our own ſouls (as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 43.) till the ſoul come to an experimental knowledge of the inward my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery and power of godlineſs in the heart, having all the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſences touched, affected, &amp; exerciſed with the delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful preſentation of their commenſurated objects, thus:<note n="*" place="margin">The inwa<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> myſtery and power of G<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deſcribed.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The heart <hi>hears</hi> the voyce of Chriſt, in the language of a ſpiritual lover, as in <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.8. <hi>The voice of my Beloved,</hi> The <hi>ellipſis</hi> and imperfect expreſſion intimateth a ſuddain ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual paſſion of the heart, leaping with joy at the found there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Of this inward voice the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>Thou ſhalt hear a voice behinde thee, ſaying, This is the way, walk in it.</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.3. <hi>Say unto my ſoul, Thou art my ſalvation.</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. <hi>Thou ſaidſt, Seek my face: thy face, Lord, will I ſeek.</hi> (That Text inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates a voice making an <hi>Eccho</hi> in the heart.) Should ſeem by this laſt place, and the reſt, that this voice is not a Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptureleſs dreamed Revelation or Enthuſiaſm; but the voice of God's written Word carried from the ear to the heart, by applications ond impreſſions of the Spirit. 2. The heart <hi>ſees</hi> the glory of the exellency of Chriſt; Viſions of faith, and raptures of admiration and adoration of him, <hi>Cant.</hi> oft. And 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. <hi>Eye hath not ſeen,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But God hath revealed them to us by his Spirit.</hi> And <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. <hi>I count all dung to the excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt.</hi> 3. The heart <hi>feels</hi> the operations of the Spirit of Chriſt, as mortifying ſin, ſo quickening, raiſing, and enlivening the ſoul in ſpiritual actings, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. much. And <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.6. <hi>While he ſpake, my ſoul failed,</hi> (Heb. <hi>my ſoul went forth</hi>) through wonderful affectionate apprehenſions. 4. The heart <hi>taſtes</hi> the ſweetneſs of Chriſt's love ſhed or poured upon the ſpiritual palat, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. 5. And laſtly, the heart <hi>ſmells</hi> the fragrant, pleaſant, acceptable communications of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:46155:17"/>Chriſt to the ſoul, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.12. <hi>While the King ſitteth at the table, my ſpikenard,</hi> viz. by communication from him, <hi>ſendeth forth the ſmell thereof:</hi> for ſo it follows in the next verſe, <hi>A bundle of myrrhe is my Beloved unto me.</hi> And v. 14. <hi>My Beloved is to me a cluſter of camphire.</hi> So the ſoul ſpeaks of Chriſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.8. <hi>All thy garments ſmell of myrrhe, aloes, and caſsia. Iacob</hi> is ſweet, but not of himſelf, but in the garments of his elder brother; by that means, he <hi>ſmells as a field of flowers whom the Lord hath bleſſed, Gen.</hi> 27. And thus <hi>(Chriſtians)</hi> we be, or muſt be, if right.</p>
            <p>The third thing to be done in relation to the Minatory Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnoſticks of evil to come,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nvention.</note> is to raiſe our Faith to believe in God through Chriſt, that (as the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Say to the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, It ſhall be well with them</hi>) it ſhall be well with us that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. This our Apoſtle hints in the Context, when he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts the <hi>Theſſalonians not to be ſhaken in minde.</hi> As we flee to Prayer for ſuccour againſt ſuch ſtorms, ſo Faith is the hand of Prayer to lay hold and climb up into God's lap. And to cheriſh our Faith, and comfort thereby, the Apoſtle tells us in the Text and Context, that if, do the good party what they can, <hi>Apoſtacie</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian impletie</hi> riſe yet higher and higher, come the worſt that can come, it ſhall not be long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ere Chriſt come. <hi>Acerbiſsima pati poſſumus, modo breviſsima.</hi> We may endure <hi>ſharp</hi> things, if <hi>ſhort.</hi> If nothing elſe can take down the high appearance of <hi>Apoſtates</hi> and <hi>Antichriſts,</hi> Chriſts appearance ſhall. Then is their total ruine, and our perpetual reſtauration; and to triumph on earth (for a time) afore the Ultimate Glory; as we have it elſewhere. That as when no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing would reſtrain ſeveral rebellions of the Iſraelites about to ſtone <hi>Moſes, Aaron,</hi> and other good men among them, <hi>The glory of the Lord</hi> appeared upon the Tabernacle, and aw'd and huſht all: ſo ſhall it be in this. Therefore with Faith, and Hope, and perſonal purity, wait. Cannot we watch with Chriſt one hour? Bleſſed are all they that ſtand ready wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for him with their loyns girt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:46155:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
